# Shengzhong Mao

CONTACT Information Department of Computer Science The University of Manchester Manchester, M13 9PL, UK Email: shengzhong.mao@manchester.ac.uk Web: Google Scholar, Homepage Tel: (+44)0753-613-6657

RESEARCH Interest My research interests cover machine learning and data mining, particularly in learning graph representations for time series data. I aim to explore temporal patterns within multivariate sequences, leveraging this insight to advance predictive strategies in practical applications.

**EDUCATION** 

Ph.D. in Computer Science

Sept. 2020 - Mar. 2024 Manchester, UK

University of Manchester

Supervisor: Prof. Xiaojun Zeng

Thesis: Visibility Graph Networks for Time Series Forecasting

Sept. 2016 - Jun. 2020 Chongqing, CN

B.Eng. in Network Engineering

Yuan Longping Class (Honors College)<sup>1</sup> Southwest University (GPA: 4.0/4.0)

**Exchage Student** 

National Chung Hsing University (GPA: 4.0/4.0)

Sept. 2017 - Jan. 2018 Taichung

**PUBLICATIONS** 

- [1] S. Mao, X. Zeng. Learning Visibility Attention Graph Representation for Time Series Forecasting. Proceedings of the 32nd ACM International Conference on Information and Knowledge Management (CIKM 2023).
- [2] S. Mao, X. Zeng. SimVGNets: Similarity-Based Visibility Graph Networks for Carbon Price Forecasting. *Expert Systems With Applications* 230 (2023) 120647.
- [3] S. Mao, X. Zeng. Multiplex Convolutional Visibility Graph Networks for Multivariate Carbon Price Forecasting. *IEEE Transactions on Knowledge and Data Engineering*. (Under Review)
- [4] S. Mao, X. Zeng. AVGNets: Angular Visibility Graph Networks with Probability Attention for Time Series Forecasting. *IJCAI 2023 Workshop on Artificial Intelligence for Time Series Analysis (AI4TS)*.
- [5] S. Mao, X. Zeng. DVGNets: Differential Visibility Graph Networks for Time Series Forecasting. Knowledge-Based Systems. (Under review)
- [6] S. Mao, C. Tseng, J. Shang, Y. Wu, X. Zeng. Construction Cost Index Prediction: A Visibility Graph Network Method. 2021 International Joint Conference on Neural Networks (IJCNN 2021).
- [7] S. Mao, Y. Deng, D. Pelusi. Alternatives selection for produced water management: A network-based methodology. Engineering Applications of Artificial Intelligence 91 (2020) 103556.
- [8] S. Mao, Y. Han, Y. Deng, D. Pelusi. A hybrid DEMATEL-FRACTAL method of handling dependent evidences. *Engineering Applications of Artificial Intelligence* 91 (2020) 103543.
- [9] **S. Mao**, F. Xiao. Time series forecasting based on complex network analysis. *IEEE Access* 7 (2019) 40220-40229.
- [10] S. Mao, F. Xiao. A novel method for forecasting Construction Cost Index based on complex network. *Physica A: Statistical Mechanics and its Applications* 527 (2019) 121306.
- [11] S. Mao, F. Xiao, Z. Cao, D. Pelusi. An adaptive visibility graph power averaging aggregation (AVGPA) operator and its application in financial time series. *Soft Computing*. (Under review)
- [12] Y. Wu, C. Tseng, J. Shang, S. Mao, N. Goran, X. Zeng. EDU-level Extractive Summarization with Varying Summary Lengths. Findings of the 17th Conference of the European Chapter of the Association for Computational Linguistics (EACL 2023).

<sup>&</sup>lt;sup>1</sup>The honors program for top-talent students, selecting no more than 1% (40 of over 9,000) students annually.

- [13] C. Tseng, S. Lee, J. Feng, S. Mao, Y. Wu, J. Shang, X. Zeng. UPANets: Learning from the Universal Pixel Attention Neworks. Entropy 24 (2022) 1243.
- [14] J. Shang, X. Zeng, Y. Wu, S. Mao and C. Tseng. A machine learning approach for functional data classification based on unified basis functions. Information Sciences. (Under Review)

#### Research EXPERIENCE

### Graph Representation Learning for Time Series Forecasting Research Assistant at Machine Learning and Robotics Group

Sept. 2020 - Mar. 2024 Manchester, UK

- Proposed weighting scheme for time series encoding by mapping binary relations into weighted networks, which overcomes information loss of graph mapping.
- Extended the concept of single-layer graph to multiplex networks, and introduced intra-layer and inter-layer similarities to extracts past and recent sequential knowledge.
- Introduced ProbAttention mechanism to evaluate probabilistic attention distribution for multivariate long-term sequence modeling and forecasting.

Related works: [1] [2] [3] [4]

## Decision Making Under Uncertainty in Complex Systems

Jun. 2019 - Sept. 2019

Research Intern at Center for Mathematics and Systems Science

Chengdu, CN

- Addressed inner and outer dependence in evidence theory under uncertainty, and achieved higher sensitivity and accuracy in transportation project selection.
- Developed a decision-making framework applicable to complex systems, applying to products and process strategies selection for produced water management.

Related works: [7] [8]

### Time Series Fusion and Prediction by Complex Networks

Mar. 2018 - Jun. 2020

Research Assistant at Information Fusion and Intelligent System Lab

Chongqing, CN

- Investigate time series data via complex networks analysis, exploring potential links in temporal networks by link prediction based on random walk.
- Proposed network-based models for time series aggregation and improved predictive accuracy on real-world datasets, offering a novel promising avenue of network forecasting.

Related works: [9] [10] [11]

#### Honors and Awards

• President's Doctoral Scholarship Award, University of Manchester (Top 1%)	2020-2023
• President's Doctoral Scholarship Development Fund (£500)	2023
• National Scholarship, China Ministry of Education (Top 1%)	2019-2020
• Innovation Funding Program, Southwest University (¥2,000)	2019-2020
• Top-Talent Students Cultivation Program, Southwest University (Top 1%)	2016-2020
• Honorable Mention, International Mathematical Contest in Modeling	2019
• First Provincial Prize, National Mathematical Contest in Modeling	2019

### Conferences &Talks

• The 32nd International Joint Conference on Artificial Intelligence@AI4TS (IJCAI'23)	2023
• ACM International Conference on Information and Knowledge Management (CIKM'23)	2023
• 2021 International Joint Conference on Neural Networks (IJCNN'21)	2021
• The 16th China Network Science Forum (CNETSCI'20)	2020

#### Professional Services

- Reviewer: Information Sciences, Information Fusion, IEEE TFS, IEEE TKDE, EAAI, etc.
- Committee Member: Computation Tools 2024
- Session Chair: CIKM 2023

### Teaching EXPERIENCE

#### Teaching Assistant

Oct. 2020 - Present

Department of Computer Science, University of Manchester

Manchester, UK

- COMP11120 Mathematical Techniques for Computer Science
- COMP11212 Fundamentals of Computation
- COMP24112 Machine Learning
- COMP26020 Programming Languages
- COMP66090 Masters Project